Guide to the Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834
4712
Antoine Laurent Lavoisier, 1743-1794. Marie-Anne-Pierrette Lavoisier, 1758-1836.
Circa 36.6 linear ft.
Manuscripts, drawings, prints, artifacts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The Lavoisier Collection contains materials by, to or about Antoine Laurent Lavoisier and his wife, Marie-Anne-Pierrette Lavoisier, née Paulze, with documents extending back to 1598 and through the death of Marie-Anne-Pierrette Lavoisier in 1836. These documents, dating mostly from 1766-1834, relate to Lavoisier's scientific work, and the Académie des Sciences, but also to his involvement in Old Regime taxation in France's Ferme Générale, and in the Régie des Poudres et Salpêtres. Also included are notes and correspondence by Marie-Anne-Pierrette Lavoisier. Many documents relate to Lavoisier's estates, mostly about Lavoisier's acquisitions of "Biens Nationaux", in Taillefontaine (France).
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Antoine Laurent Lavoisier was born in Paris in 1743. He was the son of Jean Antoine Lavoisier, a lawyer, and Émilie Punctis, who belonged to a wealthy Parisian family, and died when he was two. Then he attended the Collège Mazarin where he studied classics and mathematics. In 1763, he passed the Bachelor of Law degree. At this time he got interested in mineralogy and chemistry and attended Rouelle's classes. In 1766-1767, he went on some field trips with Jean Etienne Guettard, to study the stratigraphy of soils and make an inventory of the mineralogical resources of France.
In 1768, he was admitted to the Académie des Sciences, where he presented his research on the chemical analysis of water. The same year, he entered the Ferme Générale, a private company in charge of collecting indirect taxes for the king. Lavoisier became first an inspector of one of the Ferme Générale commissions, the Tobacco commission, where his supervisor was Jacques Paulze. On December 16, 1771, Lavoisier married his thirteen-year-old daughter, Marie-Anne-Pierrette Paulze, who was also the grandniece of the powerful Abbé Terray, the Controller General of Finance. In 1775, Lavoisier entered the Régie des Poudres et Salpêtres, a private company responsible for the production, control and refining of saltpeter and the manufacture of gunpowder in France. As a Fermier Général and a member of the Régie des Poudres et Salpêtres, Lavoisier became interested in economic theories, physiocratic ideas, agronomy, and public finance.
Simultaneously, from 1772, Lavoisier studied pneumatic chemistry, the chemistry of gases, borrowing experimental facts from English scientists, like Priestley. In 1773, he published the Opuscules physiques et chimiques, where he considered atmospheric air as a mixture, that established his reputation as a chemist. In the 1770's, he discovered that the components of air were mainly oxygen and nitrogen, and defined combustion and calcination as chemical reactions. Then, with Guyton de Morveau, Berthollet and Fourcroy he elaborated a new method of chemical nomenclature, giving chemistry a clear language, published in 1787 under the title of Méthode de nomenclature chimique. At least, in 1789, his Traité élémentaire de chimie explained the essential points of the new chemistry, like the composition of air and water and the law of the conservation of matter in chemical reactions, and depicted the experimental methods of a real scientific approach. The thirteen plates illustrating the work had been engraved by Marie-Anne Lavoisier
In 1789, Lavoisier failed to be elected at the Estates General, and steered clear of political affairs. He resigned from his office at the Ferme Générale shortly before its abolition in 1791, but was considered as an consultant in financial affairs and became the director of the Discount Bank, and a commissioner of the Public Treasury, and expressed many ideas about the reforms of French public finance and taxation. At the same time, he took part to the major reform of the unification of the weights and measures system. But, as a former Fermier Général and like his peers, among them his father-in-law, Jacques Paulze, he was arrested in 1794. They were accused of exactions and embezzlement and transferred to the Conciergerie. On the 19 floréal an II (May 8, 1794), they were all sentenced to death and executed.
After Antoine Laurent Lavoisier's death, his properties were consficated by the State. In 1795, after a campaign, Marie-Anne Lavoisier obtained the restoration of her property. In the same time, she published an edition of Lavoisier's works. In 1805, she married an American scientist, Benjamin Thomson, who had become Count Rumford in 1791.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Lavoisier collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, legal documents, plates and graphics, dating mostly from 1766-1834, from the archives of Antoine Laurent and Marie Anne Lavoisier. The contents of the collection are arranged into three broad categories: correspondence; miscellaneous documents about Lavoisier and his relatives; plates and engravings.
Letters include correspondence of Antoine Laurent Lavoisier with many scientists (physicists, chemists, mineralogists...), such as Jean Sylvain Bailly, Claude-Louis Berthollet, Jean-Antoine-Claude Chaptal, Joseph Black, Henri Louis Duhamel du Monceau, Auguste Denis Fougeroux de Bondaroy, Antoine-François Fourcroy, Jean-Louis Giraud-Soulavie, Jean Etienne Guettard, Louis-Bernard Guyton de Morveau, Joseph Louis Lagrange, Gaspard Monge. They document Lavoisier's work in areas such as the discovery of oxygen and the development of modern chemical nomenclature. But other letters also relate to Lavoisier's activities as an inspector and tax collector in France's Ferme Générale, and Régie des Poudres et Salpêtres. Also included are notes and correspondence by Marie Anne Lavoisier, from 1787 to 1825, that show her involvement in her husband's scientific work (laboratory work, translations of scientific works from the English).
Included among the manuscripts are laboratory notes from Lavoisier's experiments on the decomposition and recomposition of water, which helped to demonstrate the existence of oxygen and its role in chemical reactions. Among the other materials, some legal documents and reports relate to the Ferme Générale, the Académie des Sciences, the Régie des Poudres et Salpêtres, and the Compagnie de la Guyane française, in which Lavoisier and his father-in-law, Jacques Paulze, had holdings.
An important file of title deeds (1598-1834) relates to the acquisition of "biens nationaux" by Antoine Laurent Lavoisier, located in Taillefontaine, and to the return of these properties to his widow after his death, and their cultivation.
Also included are photocopies of documents relating to Lavoisier and gunpowder, from originals held at the Eleutherian Mills Historical Library (Greenville, Delaware). These include manuscript notes and essays on saltpeter and gunpowder, documents on the printing of assignats by Pierre Samuel Du Pont de Nemours, and documents concerning Lavoisier himself, including his death sentence and documents on the confiscation of his property.
In addition, photocopies of documents held at the Archives nationales in France relate to the Ferme Générale, the Institut national des sciences, proceedings of the revolutionary government, and Lavoisier's personal life. Documents include some of Lavoisier's correspondence, an inventory of the possessions of his mother Emilie Punctis after her death, and an inventory of Lavoisier's belongings when he was in prison.
Visual materials in the collection include some portraits of Antoine Laurent and Marie Anne Lavoisier, maps of their properties, and 81 drawings, proofs, and final plates Marie Anne Lavoisier created for her husband's Traité élémentaire de chimie in 1789.
Artifacts reflect the Lavoisiers' personal and professional activities, including two briefcases owned by Antoine Lavoisier (one when he was a child); a Masonic apron; shoe buckles; a library ladder; three small purses of jetons (metal pieces resembling coins) that Lavoisier received for attendance at meetings of government bodies, including the Académie des sciences and a committee on agriculture and commerce; a medal from the Caisse d'escompte; two small games of fortune telling; a cosmetic case designed to resemble a two-volume book; and the original copper plate for Plate VIII of the Traité elementaire de chimie.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent,1743-1794.; Bailly, Jean Sylvain, 1736-1793.; Baudon, François.; Baumé, Antoine, 1728-1804.; Beaumanoir de, baron.; Berthollet, Claude-Louis, 1748-1822.; Black, Joseph, 1728-1799.; Brisson, Mathurin-Jacques, 1723-1806.; Chaptal, Jean-Antoine-Claude, 1756-1832.; Duhamel du Monceau, 1700-1782.; Fougeroux de Bondaroy, Auguste Denis, 1732-1789.; Fourcroy, Antoine-François de, 1755-1809.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790.; Guettard, Jean Etienne, 1715-1786.; Guyton de Morveau, Louis-Bernard, 1737-1816.; La Forte, Benoist, b. 1761.; Lagrange, Joseph-Louis, 1736-1813.; Lavoisier, Jean-Antoine, 1715-1775.; Lavoisier, Marie-Anne-Pierrette, 1758-1836.; Monge, Gaspard, 1746-1818.; Morellet, André, 1727-1819.; Parisis, Nicolas Charles.; Paulze, Jacques, 1723-1794.; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804.; Saussure, Horace Bénédict de, 1740-1799.; Seguin, Armand, d. 1835.; Soulavie, Jean-Louis, 1752-1813.; Abbaye de Valsery (Coeuvres-et-Valsery, France).; Académie des sciences (France).; Aisne (France).DoMaynes nationaux.; Chapitre de la collégiale Saint-Jacques (Pierrefonds, France).; Chartreuse de Bourg-Fontaine (Villers-Cotterêts, France).; Compagnie de la Guyane française.; Couvent des Ursulines (Crépy-en-Valois, France).; France.Ferme générale.; France.Régie des poudres et salpêtres.; France.Armée--Ordnance and ordnance stores.; Paroisse Notre-Dame (Taillefontaine, France).; Prieuré du Mont Saint-Pierre en Chastres (Vieux-Moulin, France).
Subjects:
Chemistry--History--Sources.; Ordnance.; Enlightenment--France.; Taxation--France.; Finance, Public--France.; Women intellectuals--France.; Women scientists--France.; Military art and science--France--History.; Women--France--History.; Domestic relations--France--History.; Street lighting--France--Paris.; Saltpeter.; Grain trade--France.
Places:
France--History--Revolution, 1789-1794.; France--Politics and government--Revolution, 1789-1799.; France--History--Louis XVI, 1774-1793.; France--Politics and government--1774-1793.; France--Economic conditions--18th century.; France--Intellectual life--18th century.; France--Politics and government--1789-1815.; France--History--19th century.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
PROVENANCE
The bulk of the collection came down through the Chazelles family and was subsequently acquired by Lavoisier bibliographer Denis Duveen. Duveen sold the collection after finishing the bibliography. The Cornell Library purchased the collection from dealer H.P. Kraus in 1963. Additional material was collected by Pierre Dejours, and subsequently the Library purchased the Dejours material from Librairie Hatchuel in 2006.
RELATED MATERIALS
Some bound manuscripts (circa 80 v.) and a large collection of books by and about Lavoisier (circa 2,000 v.) are housed in the repository, including circa 600 v. from the Lavoisiers' personal library.
Related materials on saltpeter and gunpowder manufacture in 18th-century France are held at the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections in the La Forte Collection. Other related materials are held in the French Revolution Collection, Lafayette Collection (especially about the Compagnie de la Guyane française), Maurepas Collection, Ben Grauer Collection, and the Rare book collection.
Related collection in: Académie des Sciences (France), Fonds Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier.
NOTES
The following container list describes a part of the Lavoisier unbound manuscripts collection, that was purchased in 2005 by the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections. The rest of the unbound manuscripts collection is described in a card catalog including detailed subject and author indexes available in the Reference room of the library.
The bound manuscripts are described in the Cornell University Library catalog, under the call number 4712 Bd. Ms.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence to or from Antoine Laurent Lavoisier
1766-1786
1786-1794
Series II. Correspondence to or from Marie-Anne Lavoisier
Series III. Correspondence to or from Lavoisier's other relatives or associates
Series IV. Lavoisier and associates scientific notes and manuscripts
Lavoisier's notes and manuscripts
Associates' notes and manuscripts
Series V. Lavoisier's manuscripts on other topics
Series VI. Certificates, deeds and contracts
Deeds, contracts and certificates relating to Antoine Laurent Lavoisier
Deeds, contracts and certificates relating to Marie-Anne Lavoisier
Title deeds of "Biens nationaux", 1598-1834
Deeds made before 1789, 1598-1781
Deeds made during the French Revolution, 1791-1801
Deeds made after 1801
Series VII. Documents relating to institutions to which Lavoisier belonged
Académie des Sciences
Compagnie de la Guyane française
Régie des poudres et salpêtres
Series VIII. Documents relating to Lavoisier's relatives or associates
Series VIIIA. Photocopies of documents held at other repositories
Eleutherian Mills Historical Library
Archives nationales and other French archives
Series IX. Plates made by Marie Anne Lavoisier for the Traité élémentaire de chimie, 1789
Planche I
Planche II
Planche III
Planche IV
Planche V
Planche VI
Planche VII
Planche VIII
Planche IX
Planche X
Planche XI
Planche XII
Planche XIII
Plates engraved by J. Pass, after Marie Anne Lavoisier's work and Henry Lascelles' drawings, describing the modern chemical apparatus, London, 1800-1801.
Series X. Other Drawings
Plans of Buildings
Plans of Madame Lavoisier's Residence in Paris
Maps Used by Lavoisier as Fermier General
Mineralogical Studies
Series XI. Lavoisier Artifacts and Memorabilia
Series XII. Cesar Francois Cassini's Cartes de France
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence to or from Antoine Laurent Lavoisier
  Arranged chronologically
  - 1766-1786
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, [Villers-Cotterêts],[to]Monsieur Guettard, Paris, October 21, 1766 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      Physical Description: 4 p. on 1 leaf; 22 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: Scientific letter written during the mineralogical travel made with Jean Etienne Guettard
      Letter begins: "Monsieur et cher docteur/Il faut avouer que vous négligez furieusement ceux qui se portent bien..."
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, May 15, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm; holograph signed, seal attached
      Summary: Thanks Lavoisier for the honesty of his dealings, and asks for a monetary advance.
      Letter begins: "on n'oblige pas avec plus de grace Monsieur / mon projet était de vous remercié moy même..."
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, Paris, [to] MM. de l'Académie de Gottingue, January 19, 1774 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      Physical description: 2 p. on 1 leaf; 32 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: Lavoisier relates his role in the last discoveries in chemistry and their consequences.
      Letter begins: "Messieurs/Permettez moi de vous offrir le premier volume d'un ouvrage dans lequel je me suis proposé principalement deux objets..."
      Bibliographic Reference: 31.1.76
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent [to] Mess. De l'Académie des curieux de la nature, Paris, January 19, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 32 cm;holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Covering letter sent with gift of Opuscules physiques et chymiques (1774). Cf. Correspondance, II, no. 215, 216.
      Letter begins: "Messieurs. / Permettes moi de vous offrir le premier / volume…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Cf. Correspondance, II, no. 215, 216
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, January 28, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm; holograph signed. Seal attached
      Summary: Asks for a loan of 150 louis.
      Letter begins: "personne n'oblige avec autant de grace que vous / Monsieur je n'oublirais jamais avec quelle promtitude..."
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, February 16, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm; holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Asks that Lavoisier not refuse the loan she recently requested.
      Letter begins: "puige vous demander Monsieur si je puis espérer / que je vous devrais ma tranquilité…"
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, April 22, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Letter begins: "j'ai ésperé Monsieur recevoir de vos nouvelle / relativement aux cans Louis que je vous ai prie / de me pretter…"
    - France. Régie des poudres et salpêtres, [to] Mr. Le Brigant, ca. 1775 (Box 43, Folder 3)
      Physical description: 2 p. on 1 leaf; 23 cm; letter signed by Antoine Laurent Lavoisier
      Letter begins: "Mr. le Directeur général nous a communiqué Monsieur la lettre que vous lui avez écritte le 28 December dernier..."
      Bibliographic Reference: Scheler 1961
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent [to an unnamed woman], Paris ou Vincennes, May 10, 1775 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 22 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: M. Boudin has been appointed to desired position.
      Letter begins: "Madame / Comment osez vous écrire…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Correspondance, II, no.262
    - Guyton de Morveau, Dijon, [to] Monsieur Lavoisier, Paris, March 25, 1777 (Box 43, Folder 4)
      Physical description: 4 p. on 1 leaf; 22 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: Goes with the sending of Guyton de Morveau's Elémens de chymie théorique et pratique.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur/Je viens de charger un de mes amis qui part pour Paris d'un petit paquet pour M. Macquer dans lequel il y a un exemplaire pour vous du premier volume de notre cours de chymie..."
      Bibliographic Reference: Déc. 1962 Scheler
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent [to] Mde. Herissant, Paris, August 22, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 17 cm;holograph signed.
      Letter begins: "Mde Herissant est priée / de faire tirer 2000 exemplaires /"
      Bibliographic Reference: Correspondance, III, no. 346
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, [to] M. Morand., March 28, 1778 (Box 43, Folder 5)
      Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 12 cm; autograph letter signed
      Letter begins: "Je reconnais que M. Morand m'a remis le troisième volume du voyage en Sibérie par M. Pallas a l'académie le 28 March 1778."
      Bibliographic Reference: L'Abbaye 12.76
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, December 7, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves, 20 cm;holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Asks Lavoisier to see her notary concerning the "marc d'or."
      Letter begins: "Monsieur j'ai été à La Campagne..."
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, Paris, [to] Mlle Bégon., January 17, 1780 (Box 43, Folder 6)
      Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 21 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: Payment of an annuity.
      Letter begins: "Mademoiselle/J'ai l'honneur de vous faire passer une rescription de 1168 l. sur le receveur des Aydes de Blois... "
      Bibliographic Reference: Scheler/Fév. 1962
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent [to] Mlle. Begon, Paris, June 27, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Summary: Forwards payment for salt storage at Vendosme. Related notes in different hand on p. [4].
      Letter begins: "Mademoiselle / Comme j'avais été instruit par M. votre frère…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Correspondance, III, no. 422
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent [to] M. d'Angiviller, October 16, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 25 cm;holograph.
      Summary: Draft thanking d'Angiviller for having enabled Lavoisier to try out the new lighting system for opera houses.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / J'ai bien de remerciements à vous faire…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Correspondance, III, no. 428
    - Soulavie, Jean-Louis, Paris, [to Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent]., April 12, 1782 (Box 43, Folder 7)
      Physical Description: 4 p. on 1 leaf; 21 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: Soulavie asks Lavoisier to see the residuum from his experiments on quartz.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur/Très souvent j'ai passé chez vous pour avoir l'honneur de m'instruire chés un savant distingué et jaMays je n'ai pu jouir de cette faveur..."
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, [draft for an answer] to M. l'abbé Soulavie., April 1782 (Box 43, Folder 7)
      Summary: Draft for answering Soulavie.
      Letter begins: "M. l'abbé Soulavie/Lui consigner mon regret de... les expériences que j'ai faittes sur le quartz et le cristal de roche ayans été faittes sur de très petits échantillons..."
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent [to] M. Poiré Lutrepot, Le Villars, April 25, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 23 cm;holograph signed.
      Summary: Agrees to extend loan arrangement for a second year. Schedule of payments in different hand on p. [2].
      Letter begins: "Je consens avec plaisir, Monsieur à vous accorder…"
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, July 10, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Summary: Requests a written account of payments Lavoisier made to her and her husband's family, and a schedule of future payments.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur je suis au moment de rendre mon / compte de tutel…"
    - Bailly, Jean-Sylvain,, [to Antoine Laurent Lavoisier], December 26, 1784 (Box 43, Folder 8)
      Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf, 15 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: Introduces Saladin, citizen of Geneva, to Lavoisier
      Letter begins: "Je prends la liberté, Monsieur et cher confrère, de vous adresser M. Saladin citoyen distingué de Genève..."
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent [to] M. Chastenet, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 22 cm; holograph.
      Summary: Draft listing sums received for the de Tocquinys in 1784 and 1785, to accompany an account of transactions made for them prior to 1784.
      Letter begins: "M. Chastenet procureur au parlement rue […] / ou en son absence à M. Ducolombier…"
    - Soulavie, Jean-Louis, [autograph letter signed] Paris, [to Antoine Laurent Lavoisier], April 8, 1785 (Box 43, Folder 9)
      Physical Description: 3 p. on 1 leaf; 22 cm
      Summary: Goes with the sending of Soulavie's Histoire naturelle de la France méridionale. Asks to enter the Société Royale.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur/J'ay eu l'honneur de vous adresser les 8 volumes d'histoire naturelle. Je serai assurément très flatté de l'honneur d'appartenir à la Société Royale..."
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, [to] Mlle Bégon, Vendosme, July 6, 1785 (Box 43, Folder 10)
      Letter begins: "Mademoiselle/J'ay l'honneur de vous adresser cy joint un rescription de 1407 l. Pour le payement des six mois de rente..."